看看这张阿拉伯沙漠的照片，
Take a look at this photo of the Arabian desert
你会发现人类历史上最雄心勃勃的
and you'll see that one of the most ambitious
建设项目之一正在推进。
construction projects in history is on.
一条200米宽的沟槽从汉志山脉一路延伸至亚喀巴湾。
A 200 m wide trench runs from the Hijaz Mountains to the Gulf of Akoba.
不仅如此，你再来看看这个。
Not only that, but take a look at this.
这是有史以来规模最大基础工程的第一段。
The first portion of what will be the biggest set of foundations ever built.
如今混凝土已经凝固，第一批垂直结构即将破土而出。
And now that concrete has set, the first vertical structures are about to emerge.
换句话说，那个人人都说
In other words, the thing that everyone said
不可能建造、永远不会建造的项目，
would never be built, could never be built,
如今正在实实在在地建造着。
is actually being built.
真的吗？
Or is it?
>> 我记得他说过："我们希望今年年底能开始向上建。"
>> I believe he said, "We're going to start going vertical hopefully at the end of this year."
在房地产领域，希望不是策略
Generally, in real estate, hope is not a strategy
>> 因为每一个进展的迹象背后，都有预算问题
>> because for every sign of progress, there's budget issues
>> 最终陷入停滞。
>> winding to a halt.
>> 沙特阿拉伯已要求咨询公司对THE LINE展开战略审查。
>> Saudi Arabia has asked consulting firms to conduct a strategic review of the line.
甚至有传言称整个项目已经被叫停。
There are even rumors swirling that the whole thing has been cancelled.
但我们究竟掌握了哪些确切信息？
But what do we actually know?
2026年将是THE LINE的生死关头。
2026 is going to be make or break for the line.
今年是必须兑现承诺的一年，
This is the year when deadlines need to be met
进展将以高度来衡量，而不是靠宣传造势。
and when progress is going to be measured in height, not hype.
因为无论你怎么看待这个项目，这个想法究竟现实吗？
Because regardless of what you think of this project, this idea even realistic.
>> 这简直荒唐透顶。
>> That is absolutely insane.
>> 有一个国家的未来押注于此，
>> There's a country whose future depends on it
有一位领导人押上了他全部的声誉。
and a leader who staked his entire reputation on it.
他们说这能做到。
they say can be done.
他们不能一直这样说，而我们也不能一直证明他们是错的。
They can't keep saying that and we can't keep proving them wrong.
那么，它究竟会建成吗？
So, will it ever be built?
让我们来探个究竟。
Let's find out.
如果你不是消息闭塞的话，那你一定知道这就是THE LINE。
So, in case you've been living under a rock, this is the line.
这是沙特阿拉伯规划中的大型线性城市（linear city）。
Saudi Arabia's plan for a massive linear city.
建成后，它将成为NEOM的首府。
When or if it's complete, it'll form the capital of Neome.
NEOM是该国西北部一片广袤的全新区域，由这位穆罕默德·本·萨勒曼王储一手构想。
A vast new region in the country's northwest dreamed up by this guy, Crown Prince Muhammad bin Salman.
它是他2030愿景（Vision 2030）的组成部分——
It forms part of his vision 2030, an ambitious plan
一项雄心勃勃的计划，目标是在2030年前让沙特摆脱对石油的依赖。
to wean the country off its oil dependency by, you guessed it, 2030.
而THE LINE背后的数字令人瞠目结舌。
Now, the numbers behind the line are staggering.
它将宽200米、高500米，
It's going to be 200 m wide by 500 m tall
横贯沙漠绵延170公里。
and it will run for 170 km across the desert.
说实话，我甚至无法想象如此庞大的规模。
Now, I don't know about you, but I can't even begin to get my head around something that big.
所以我干脆不费那个脑筋了。
So, I'm not even trying.
我正在用乐高积木搭建一个THE LINE的迷你模型，只有两块砖高。
I'm building my own little Lego model of the line using little Lego bricks, only two bricks high.
我搭的这个模型是实际THE LINE的0.03%大小。
The model I'm building here is 0.03% the size of the actual line.
为了让你感受一下这个比例，这就是帝国大厦（Empire State Building）。
And to give you a sense of that scale, this would be the Empire State Building.
你会发现THE LINE的高度会把它彻底碾压，但你再看看它延伸得有多远。
You can see the line would absolutely dwarf it in height, but just look how far it stretches.
所以，我和世界上大多数人心中最迫切的问题是：
So, the burning question that I and much of the rest of the world has
你到底怎么建这样的东西？
is how the hell do you build something like this?
先从基础说起。
Let's start with the basics.
THE LINE要穿越地形极其多变的区域。
The line crosses lots of wildly varying terrain.
有坚硬的山岩、松软的开阔沙漠，还有含盐量高的沿海平原。
Hard mountain rock, soft open desert, and salty coastal plains.
要在如此多变的地形上建造任何东西，首先需要一个均匀稳固的地基。
To build anything across such a varied landscape, you first need a uniform, stable footing.
这就是基础工程的用武之地。
And that's where the foundations come in.
假设我想建一座摩天大楼，但地面条件非常糟糕。
Say I want to build a skyscraper, but the ground I'm trying to build my skyscraper on is rubbish.
这个豆袋是用来代表一种叫做第四纪沉积物（quaternary deposits）的东西，
Now, this bean bag is to represent something called cturnary deposits,
简单来说就是松散堆积、未经压实的材料，
which is basically a really fancy way of saying loosely deposited material
承载任何重量都极不可靠。
that hasn't been compacted and is pretty terrible for putting any kind of weight through.
这正是THE LINE大部分地段地表以下的状况。
This is what you're going to find under much of the sight of the light.
然而，在这些松散材料之下深处，是基岩（bedrock），
However, below that down here through all this material is bedrock,
那才是建造建筑物的理想基础。
and that's a great surface for putting a building on.
怎么到达那里？
How do I get down there?
我需要建造一种叫做桩筏基础（piled raft foundation）的结构，大概是这个样子。
Well, I have to create something called a piled raft foundation, which looks a little bit like this.
在地面这里有一块坚实的混凝土板。
So, I get a nice solid concrete slab on top here at ground level.
建筑的重量从这里向下传递，穿过所有这些糟糕的地质层。
And then the weight of my building gets carried down, transferred through all this terrible material here.
这些地层本身不承受重量。
There's no weight going on it.
重量通过桩基（piles）向下传导到坚实的基岩上。
Instead, the weight's being pushed down through the piles down here into that solid bedrock.
这样我就有了一个极为出色的摩天大楼建造基础。
What I'm left with here is an absolutely outstanding surface for building a skyscraper on.
好，这听起来可能很简单，但剧透一下，绝对不简单。
Okay, that probably makes it sound pretty simple, but spoiler alert, it's most definitely not.
为任何建筑设计基础，尤其是这种规模的，都需要大量复杂的计算。
Designing foundations for any building, let alone one of this size, takes a ton of calculation.
而要完成这些计算，你需要强大的算力，
And for that, you need some serious muscle,
这就是AMD Threadripper Pro 9000WX系列处理器登场的时刻了。
which is where the AMD Threader Pro 9000WX series of processors comes in.
有"Thread Ripper（线程撕裂者）"这样的名字，难怪它会成为建筑行业最受青睐的芯片之一。
Now, with a name like Thread Ripper, it's no surprise that this is one of the go-to chips in the world of construction.
玩笑归玩笑，这款芯片是建筑、工程和施工行业的基石，
Joking aside, the chip is a cornerstone of the architecture, engineering, and construction industries
因为它专为高强度多任务工作流而生。
because it's built for intense multifunctional workflows.
Threadripper Pro拥有多达96个核心，远超普通高端桌面处理器，
Thread Ripper Pro packs up to 96 cores, way more than a standard high-end desktop,
同时配备庞大的三级缓存（L3 cache），
and it combines that with a massive L3 cache,
能近乎即时地访问海量数据集，
which gives it near instant access to huge data sets,
堪称仿真、渲染和建模的完美利器。
perfect for simulation, rendering, and modeling.
换句话说，它是为设计建筑的人、
In other words, it's created for the people who design the building,
建造建筑的人，
those who construct the building,
以及制作那些让我们忍不住流口水的超炫效果图的人量身打造的。
and the people who create those super slick renders that we all love drooling over.
但2025年谈处理能力，怎能绕开AI。
But we can't mention processing power in 2025 without talking about AI.
Threadripper Pro内置对生成式AI工作负载的支持，大语言模型、扩散模型，应有尽有。
Thread Ripper Pro includes built-in support for generative AI workloads, large language models, diffusion models, you name it.
无论你是在开发AI工具，还是用AI辅助设计，
Whether you're developing AI tools or designing with them,
这款芯片都能给你足够的算力和内存余量，让你保持领先。
this chip gives you the compute and memory headroom to keep up.
当然，不必只听我一面之词。
But don't just take my word for it.
点击下方链接了解Threadripper Pro 9000WX系列。
Check out the Thread for Pro 9000WX series at the link below.
这既是对我们的支持，也是向行业最高标准的升级。
You'll be helping us out and upgrading to the industry's highest standard.
现在，让我们回到基础工程。
Now, let's get back to those foundations.
需要的桩基数量和深度，
The number of piles you need and the depth they go to
会因建筑规模和地质条件的不同
varies massively depending on the size of what you're building
而存在巨大差异。
and the soil underneath it.
帝国大厦有55根桩基，打入曼哈顿基岩16米深。
The Empire State Building has 55 piles dropping down 16 m into the Manhattan bedrock.
世界最高建筑哈利法塔（Burj Khalifa）则有194根桩基，深入地下43米。
The Burj Khalifa, the world's tallest building, has 194 piles sunk 43 m into the Earth.
而THE LINE目前的施工规模，远超人类历史上的任何先例。
But the work currently underway on the line dwarfs anything ever seen before.
一期工程（Phase 1）已打入逾16,000根桩基，深度达到70米。
Phase 1 has seen over 16,000 piles driven up to 70 m deep into the Saudi sand.
这相当于近1,000公里的钻探作业，使用了多达350万立方米的混凝土。
That's nearly 1,000 km of drilling using up to 3.5 million cub m of concrete.
在此之上，一层8米厚的筏板
On top of that, an 8 m thick raft will form the basis
将构成整个宏大项目的基础承台。
for everything else that this colossal project promises.
为此，一座自动化工厂正不停运转，生产数以万计长达32米的钢筋笼（rebar cages），
To pull it off, an automated factory is churning out tens of thousands of 32 m long rebar cages
用于加固每根桩基。
to reinforce each pile.
与此同时，钻机借助GPS精准定位，
Meanwhile, drilling rigs are using GPS to precisely bore the holes
钻出将要放入钢筋笼的孔洞。
that these rebar cages are going to be dropped into.
在浇筑混凝土之前，孔内会注入一种可生物降解的液体，
A biodegradable liquid is pumped into the holes to stop them from collapsing
防止孔壁坍塌。
before concrete can then be poured in.
但工程师们面对的不只是松软的土层。
But it's not just soft earth that engineers have to grapple with.
由于紧邻大海，这一地段还需要抵御盐度极高的地下水侵蚀。
Being so close to the sea, this stretch also needs protecting from the highly saline groundwater.
如不加以处理，高盐地下水会逐渐锈蚀钢筋笼，腐蚀混凝土桩基。
Left untreated, it could rust the steel cages over time and corrode the concrete piles.
为此，世界上规模最大的降水系统（dewatering system）应运而生。
Now, to solve this, the world's largest dewatering system has been created.
沿THE LINE这段区域钻设了500口水井，
500 wells were drilled along this stretch of the line.
每口井底都安装了一台水泵。
each equipped with a water pump at its bottom.
系统以每小时90,000立方米的速度抽水，
Water is pumped out at a rate of 90,000 cubic meters an hour
输送至沉淀池，在那里对水质进行检测。
or towards a settlement pond where the quality of the liquid is checked.
之后，水经过过滤，通过一系列排放管道被抽送入海。
From there, the water is filtered and pumped out to sea in a series of discharge pipes.
一期工程的基础施工已接近尾声，
Work on the foundations for phase 1 is nearly complete,
这意味着项目即将迈入下一个里程碑——向上建。
which means the project is about to enter its next milestone, going vertical.
对于典型的摩天大楼来说，这意味着开始建造核心筒（core）。
On a typical skyscraper, that means building the core.
如果你曾路过建筑工地，多半见过这种结构拔地而起。
If you ever walked past a construction site, you'll probably have seen these going up.
它们外观并不好看，但对摩天大楼的运作至关重要。
They're not that attractive, but they're critical to how a skyscraper works.
本质上，它是建筑的骨架，
You see, it's essentially the backbone of the building,
通过将混凝土浇入模具、
and it's formed by pouring concrete into a mold
再由液压千斤顶（hydraulic jacks）不断顶升来成型。
that gets pushed up by hydraulic jacks.
但THE LINE有一个不同之处。
But with the line, there's a twist.
为了解释这一点，我再次借助乐高。
And to explain that, I am once again resorting to Lego.
别忘了，THE LINE是一座城市。
So, don't forget that the line is a city.
它是一个框架体系。
It's a framework.
它不是一栋单一的建筑。
It's not a single building.
所以它内部不会有一根贯穿170公里的单一核心筒。
So it doesn't have one single core that stretches for 170 km inside it.
相反，它由数以千计的核心筒组成，每一个都像普通楼宇一样单独建造。
Instead, it's made up of thousands of cores, each built individually just like any other core.
但关键在于，这些核心筒支撑着你看到的黄色甲板，
But crucially, these support the yellow decks you can see here,
也就是整个结构的主层（primary decks）。
which are going to be the primary decks of the structure.
这些主层就像城市的主干道、主要大道，
They're like the kind of the main streets, the main avenues,
而核心筒则是横向的街道。
and the cores are going to be the cross streets.
就像曼哈顿的街道网格，只不过想象它被折叠起来，垂直叠放。
It's just like the Manhattan grid except imagine it folded up and stacked vertically.
城市的真正活力，将在这个框架之内迸发。
It's here within this framework where the city is going to really come to life.
学校、医院、住宅、交通基础设施，一切让城市运转的要素都将在此汇聚。
You'll find schools, hospitals, homes, transport infrastructure, everything you need to make a city function.
这正是目前正在建造的内容。
This is what's currently under construction.
两排500米高的塔楼。
Two rows of 500 meter towers.
一期工程将吊装480万吨钢外伸臂梁（steel outrigger beams），
Phase one will see 4.8 8 million tons of steel outrigger beams hoisted up
以支撑贯穿其间的五层主层结构。
to support the five decks running through each.
在普通摩天大楼建设中，钢结构和外墙装饰会在这一阶段之前就开始安装。
Usually on skyscrapers, the steel work and cladding will start to be added before you get to this stage.
它们基本上是跟着核心筒一路向上推进，
They basically follow the core up the building,
这也是2026年令人期待的原因——
which is why 2026 is so exciting
届时建设应当真正成形，
because things should really start to take shape
进度也会明显加快。
and we should start to see some fast progress.
这就是那个数十亿……抱歉，我是说数万亿美元的问题。
That is the billiondoll sorry I mean trillion dollar question.
先从混凝土说起。
Let's start by talking about concrete.
大规模浇筑混凝土极为复杂。
Now pouring concrete at scale is incredibly complex.
浇筑太慢，混凝土会凝固不均。
Pour it too slowly and it'll set unevenly.
但浇筑太快，原材料可能会离析分层。
But pour it too fast and the ingredients can split.
配比过湿，混凝土会变脆。
Get the mixture too wet and your concrete's going to be brittle.
太干，则会变得像瑞士奶酪一样千疮百孔。
Too dry and it'll end up like Swiss cheese.
说到底，这需要长时间保持绝对的一致性。
Basically, it relies on total consistency for long periods of time.
目前已经浇筑了数百万吨混凝土，这是相当扎实的施工记录。
Now, millions of tons of concrete have already been poured, which is a pretty solid track record.
但那是在海岸附近，可以方便地获取供应。
But that's here on the coast with access to supply lines.
这座城市还有漫长的路要走，要深入广袤的腹地，
This city still has a very long way to go up into a vast hintterland
那里既没有本地建材，也极度缺乏一种关键原料——水。
with no access to local materials and a near total lack of one very key ingredient, water.
但有一个方案。
But there's a plan.
一切从OXAGON开始，这是NEOM的另一个大型项目，
It all begins here at the Oxigon, another of NEM's mega projects
一座大型海水淡化厂（desalination plant）将把数十亿升海水
where a massive desalination plant is going to pump billions of lers of seawater
泵送至沿城市全线分布的蓄水库。
to reservoirs dotted along the length of the city.
这些蓄水库将为一个耗资1.9亿美元的混凝土工厂网络提供水源，
They'll feed a 190 million US network of concrete factories
每天可生产20,000立方米混凝土。
capable of producing 20,000 cub m of concrete every day.
但问题来了。
But there's a catch.
目前为止，这一切都尚不存在。
As it stands, none of this currently exists.
OXAGON的建设直到2025年中才刚刚启动。
Work on oxygen only began in mid 2025.
那些大型混凝土工厂距离落成还遥遥无期，
Those vast concrete plants are still a very long way off
目前混凝土靠本地生产，用水则由油罐车运输，
and concrete's currently being produced locally with water shipped in by tankers,
这绝非可扩展的解决方案。
which is by no means a scalable solution.
事实上，近来又有未经证实的报道称，该海水淡化厂已被悄然搁置。
In fact, yet again, there have recently been unconfirmed reports that the desalination plant has been quietly scrapped.
我在这里可不是在吹毛求疵。
I'm not just splitting hairs here.
THE LINE在不到9年的时间内还有相当宏大的目标要实现。
The line has got some very ambitious targets to meet in less than 9 years time.
NEOM体育场将悬挂在THE LINE内部350米的高空，
The Neome Stadium is set to be suspended 350 m up in the air inside the line
并预定承办2034年FIFA世界杯的比赛。
and is set to host games at the 2034 FIFA World Cup.
届时球迷们都会买票入场的。
Games that people are going to be buying tickets for.
说实话，要让人相信这一点，我现在就希望看到更多可扩展推进的实质证据。
And to be honest, for that to be credible by this stage, I'd expect to see a lot more evidence of scalable activity.
但在2025年底站在这里，眼前的一切
Instead, what it looks like as I stand here at the end of 2025
更像是一个急于建点什么、任何东西都行，
is a project that's trying to build something, anything,
只求积攒些势头、证明批评者错误的项目。
just to gain a bit of momentum and prove people wrong.
那么，他们到底在建什么？
So, what are they actually building?
我们一直提到的一期工程究竟是什么？
What is this phase one we keep mentioning?
当你看到这片沙漠里的巨大沟壑时，你以为会建造什么？
Well, when you saw this and this massive trench in the desert, what did you think was going to be built?
也许是全部，或者一半，至少四分之一吧。然而，都不是。
Maybe the whole thing or maybe half or at least a quarter. Well, no.
尽管在沙漠中挖出了那条绵延170公里的巨型沟槽，
Despite building that enormous 170 km long cutting through the desert,
实际上他们只是在建造这一期工程——仅仅是THE LINE中区区2.4公里的一段。
they're actually only building this phase 1, a mere 2.4 km of the line.
别误会，这本身仍是一栋绝对庞大的建筑，
Now, don't get me wrong, it's still an absolutely musive building in its own right,
但它不过占整条THE LINE结构的不到1.5%。
but it accounts for less than one and a half% of the entire line structure.
你可能会觉得有点大失所望。我确实如此。
You might be feeling a little bit short changed by that. I know I certainly am.
但这背后有一定的策略考量。
But there is a bit of strategy here.
你看，NEOM团队正在利用一期工程
You see, the Neome team are using phase 1
来建造城市中最具规模、最为壮观的一批锚点资产（anchor assets）。
to construct some of this city's biggest and most spectacular anchor assets.
所谓锚点资产，就是一旦建成，便能吸引周边投资与发展的项目。
An anchor asset is something that once it is completed attracts investment and development around that area.
一个绝佳的例子就是曼哈顿的高线公园（Highline），对吧？
A really great example would be the Highline in Manhattan, right?
那本是一段废弃的高架铁轨，后来被改造成了一座公共公园。
It was this elevated sort of derelict abandoned rail tracks and it was revitalized and turned into a public park.
正是由于那个项目，高线公园周边如今已成为曼哈顿最炙手可热、价格最高昂的地段之一。
And because of that project, now that area around the Highline has become one of the most expensive and coveted areas in Manhattan.
>> 整个结构被划分为800米长的模块（modules）。
>> The whole structure is divided into 800 m long modules.
把它们想象成THE LINE的街区或社区单元。
Think of these as being like the neighborhoods or city blocks of the line.
一期工程将在场地西端建造其中三个模块，
Phase one is going to see three of these built near the western end of the site
汇聚城市最为壮观的几大特色设施。
containing some of the city's most spectacular features.
届时将建有一座可停靠世界最大邮轮的人工码头、
There's going to be a man-made marina capable of hosting the world's biggest cruise ships,
46,000人容量的NEOM体育场，
the 46,000 capacity neon stadium,
以及悬挂于入口处如同巨型枝形吊灯的迎宾构筑物。
and hanging below a vast chandelier welcoming people into this giant structure.
NEOM在这里所做的，本质上是在说：
What Neon is trying to do here is basically say
我们将出资建造一批锚点资产，
we're going to fund and build a collection of anchor assets
下一阶段的发展将在此基础上有机展开。
around which sort of the the next phase will organically take place.
这就是这里所宣称的目标。
That is the that is the that is the stated goal here.
>> 从很多角度来看，这确实很有道理。
>> Now in many ways that makes a lot of sense.
这是一套基于行业通行标准的成熟策略。
It's a sophisticated strategy based on industry-wide standards.
问题在于，这是一座坐落在沙漠中、绵延170公里的城市。
Where it doesn't make sense is that this is a 170 km long city in the desert.
THE LINE本应是一座彻底打破常规、
The line is supposed to be a revolutionary city
以最大胆的方式颠覆我们对城市认知的
that tears up the rule book in the most audacious way possible
革命性城市。
and changes the way we think about our cities forever.
对于一个权力不受约束的雄心勃勃的领导人来说，
For an ambitious leader with unchecked power,
这正是那种能够俘获全世界想象力的项目。
it's exactly the type of project you take on to capture the world's imagination.
但对其他所有人来说，这是一场巨大的赌博。
But for everyone else, it's a huge risk.
>> 我们常说，开发是一场里亚尔和哈拉拉的游戏，对吧？
>> We like to say that development is a dollars and cents game
or in this case a real and halahas game, right?
你必须对成本保持近乎疯狂的专注。
You have to be so maniacally focused on cost.
然而，在这里，这个项目既是一个建设工程，
However, here this development is part construction project
也是沙特阿拉伯未来蓝图的某种象征，对吧？
and part sort of symbol for what Saudi Arabia can become, right?
而这一切都可以追溯到最高层。
And it goes all the way to the top.
王储MBS是每个人最终向其负责的那个人。
The crown prince MBS is the one that everyone ultimately answers to.
问题就来了：他得到的是真实的信息吗？
So the question becomes, is he being told the truth?
他得到的是他真正需要知道的内容吗？
Is he being told exactly what he needs to know?
NEOM的领导层是否有足够的底气，对王储某些更为天马行空的设想说不？
Is there leadership strong enough on Neome to push back on, let's say, some of the Prince's more fantastical visions?
因为他随时可能走进来说："哦，我实际上想让它朝这个方向弯，
Because he may go in and say, "Oh, I actually want this to curve this way,
或者我想让它跨越这个东西。"
or I want this to kind of jump over this thing."
他脑子里每一个这样的念头，都可能转化为数十亿美元的成本超支（cost overruns）
And each of those ideas in his head can turn into billions of dollars of cost overruns
和数月乃至数年的工期延误，对吧？
and months or even years of delays, right?
而这对大规模开发来说，根本行不通。
And that doesn't really work well for large scale development.
THE LINE自宣布以来，就面临着围绕其所谓人道代价的激烈批评。
Ever since the line was announced, it's faced intense criticism around its alleged human cost.
>> 住宅、学校、医院——从地图上抹去。
>> Homes, schools, hospitals wiped off the map.
>> 有指控称工地上存在现代奴役行为，
>> There have been allegations of using modern-day slavery on sites
以及对拒绝搬迁的部族成员下达处决令。
and orders to execute tribes people who refuse to relocate.
这些指控遭到NEOM和沙特阿拉伯政府的强烈否认。
Allegations that Neom and the Saudi Arabian government vehemently deny.
除此之外，我们和其他记者很难、甚至根本无法真正进入施工现场，
Beyond that, it's been very difficult slash impossible for us or any journalists
当然，沙特阿拉伯对待媒体的方式
to gain real access to the sites,
与其他地方本就截然不同。
though relationships with the press are of course approached very differently in Saudi Arabia.
但这堵沉默之墙，给整个项目的根基蒙上了一层阴影。
But that wall of silence casts a shadow over the fundamentals of this project.
为了这个视频，我们联系了数十位与THE LINE相关的人士，
We reached out to dozens of people involved in the line for this video,
几乎没有人愿意出镜受访，都担心遭到报复。
and almost nobody would talk to us for fear of reprisals.
残酷的现实是，当沙特阿拉伯致力于成为一个更加进步的社会，
The hard truth is that as Saudi Arabia works to become a more progressive society,
努力在2030愿景框架下推动文化变革时，
as it works to change its culture as part of that vision 2030 plan,
它必须学会处理好与境外自由媒体的关系。
it's going to have to learn to master its relationship with the free press beyond its borders.
>> 质疑这个项目的人，在某种程度上都撞上了这堵文化的高墙。
>> People who are asking questions about this project are running into that clash of cultures in a way.
你想搞清楚为什么成本翻了三倍，或者为什么某个方案被替换，或者为什么有些东西改变了，或者为什么
You want to understand why costs have tripled or why this has been replaced or why this has changed or why there's been no updates
某某项目迟迟没有进展，但你面对的依然是一个向来不需要向任何人交代的地方。
on XYZ, but you're still dealing with a place that is used to not having to answer to anybody.
如果THE LINE真的建成，它并不会是第一座从零开始建造的城市。
Now, if the line does get built, it won't be the first showpiece city constructed from scratch.
这就是巴西利亚（Brasília）。
This is Brazilia.
1960年建城，取代里约热内卢成为巴西的首都。
Founded in 1960, it replaced Rio de Janeiro as Brazil's capital.
与THE LINE一样，它建在一个当时被视为偏远荒蛮的地方。
Just like the line, it was built in what was perceived as a remote and inhospitable location.
更与THE LINE相似的是，这座城市的规划方案是前所未有的。
And even more like the line, the city's plan was like nothing anyone has seen before.
它设计于20世纪50年代的喷气时代，
It was designed in the 1950s, the jet age,
彼时航空技术飞速发展，
when rapid advances in aviation, and the jet set
"喷气族"代表着一切前沿与未来。
represented all that was cutting edge and futuristic.
巴西利亚，意在展示一个在现代重生的国家。
Brazilia was meant to represent a country reborn in the modern era.
因此，它被设计成飞机的形状。
So, it was designed like an airplane.
政府大楼坐落于机头，
Government buildings are housed in the cockpits
住宅区沿机翼铺展，
with housing laid out on the wings
军事区则位于机尾。
and a military district in the tail.
机身形成一条宏伟的主轴，贯通全城。
The fuselage forms a monumental axis uniting the whole city.
与巴西利亚一样，THE LINE某种程度上也是一个国家为自己塑造新时代前瞻性符号的尝试。
Just like Brazilia, the line is kind of an attempt to create a new forward-looking symbol for a nation.
只不过，它的灵感不是来自蓝天，而是来自科幻小说的页面。
But rather than looking to the skies, it takes inspiration from the pages of science fiction.
我突然收到一封来自一位沙特阿拉伯女性的邮件，
Out of the blue, I got an email from a Saudi Arabian woman
邀请我就THE LINE的美学风格提供意见，
inviting me to talk with her about giving input into the aesthetics of the line
她明确表示，王储对赛博朋克（cyberpunk）非常感兴趣。
and she made it clear that he was very interested in cyberpunk.
>> 克里斯·哈布尔斯·格雷是一位学者和作家，撰写了大量关于赛博朋克及其他议题的著作。
>> Chris Hables Gray is an academic and author who's written extensively about cyberpunk and other topics.
THE LINE本身似乎部分灵感来源于《雪崩》（Snow Crash）——
The line itself seems to be based in part on something from Snow Crash,
一部小说，其中的虚拟现实世界
a novel where the virtual reality world was built around one long street,
围绕一条无限延伸的虚拟长街而建。
an almost infinite virtual street.
>> 即使你对这个词不熟悉，
>> Even if you're not familiar with the term,
你也一定在各处见过赛博朋克的美学风格，
you're going to have seen the cyberpunk aesthetic everywhere,
从电子游戏到电视剧，再到《银翼杀手》（Blade Runner）这样的电影。
from video games to TV shows and movies like Bladeunner.
克里斯是为THE LINE前身项目提供背景研究的少数几位人士之一，
Chris was one of a handful of people asked to provide background research for what we now know as the line
>> 我收集了大量赛博朋克及相关科幻类型文学中的图片和引文，
>> and I collected a lot of images and quotes from cyberpunk and related types of science fiction writing
我认为他们可能会觉得有用，
that I thought they might find useful
我被告知要重点关注城市规划、赛博朋克的城市理念，以及相关的所谓"朋克"流派。
and so I was told to look especially at urban planning urban ideas of cyber punk but also the related so-called punk genres.
我没能亲历，但有几位人士在场。
I didn't get to see this but several people were there.
王储确实出席了一场定期举办的展示或展览，汇聚了大量这类理念，
The prince did arrive at a scheduled demonstration or exhibition of a lot of these ideas
据说主要就是一些大幅图片。
which they said was mainly just big images.
于是他挑选了自己喜欢的，据说这些内容后来被融入了整座城市的建设规划中。
So then he chose what he liked and uh these was theoretically incorporated into the plans for building the whole city.
>> 这些是克里斯与NEOM分享的部分图片。
>> These are some of the images that Chris shared with Neome.
看着它们，你能清晰地看到与THE LINE早期阶段发布的概念图之间的明显关联。
Looking at them, you can see the clear link with the concept images released in the early stages of the line.
如果说THE LINE有哪一方面真的像是从电子游戏里走出来的，
If there's one aspect of the line that does seem straight out of a video game,
那就是覆盖整个建筑外立面的
it's the distinctive mirror finish
标志性镜面外观。
that covers every patch of the building's exterior.
镜面玻璃并不是什么新鲜事物，但它确实存在一些弊端。
Now, reflective glass isn't anything new, but it does come with some disadvantages.
建筑上使用的这类玻璃，是通过一种被称为溅射镀膜（sputter coating）的工艺，
The type used on buildings is made by transferring metal deposits onto glass
在高压气体环境下将金属沉积物转移到玻璃上制成的。
through a highly charged gas, a process known as sputter coating.
这种工艺在大规模生产时效率尚可，但玻璃略带透明感，反射率最多只有40%左右。
It's effective to produce at scale, but slightly translucent and at best only reflects around 40% of light.
换句话说，它永远不可能达到这个效果。
In other words, it'll never be as good as this.
这是马里亚（Mariah）。
This is Mariah.
这是一座建于2019年的非凡建筑，被认为是THE LINE的重要灵感来源之一。
It's a remarkable building that was constructed in 2019 and is thought to have been a key inspiration for the line.
起初，它以抛光金属板包覆外墙，但这些金属板很快就在恶劣的风沙环境中受损变质。
At first, it was clad in polished metal sheets, but these quickly spoiled in the harsh sandy environment.
要实现完美的镜面效果，你需要的是真正的镜子。
For a perfect mirror finish, you need a mirror.
但镜子很脆弱。
But mirrors are fragile.
在沙漠极端高温下，将镜面层压在一起的胶合层可能失效，
In the extreme heat of the desert, the lamination that binds them can fail,
镀银涂层也可能从基底上剥落。
and the silver coating can peel away from its backing.
为了生产出能够经受这些恶劣条件的产品，一种全新类型的镜子被研发出来。
To produce something that could withstand those conditions, an entirely new type of mirror was developed.
通常，镜子由普通玻璃制成。
Normally, you'd make a mirror from standard glass.
先生产大块玻璃板，裁切至所需尺寸，再涂上银质镜面层。
Large sheets are produced, cut to size, and then coated with a silver finish.
但为了承受极端温度，玻璃还必须经过热处理，即钢化（tempered）。
But to survive the extreme temperatures, this glass would also have to be heat treated or tempered.
而镜面涂层只能在钢化之后才能施加。
The mirror coating could only be applied after tempering.
但钢化玻璃（tempered glass）无法再切割。
But tempered glass can't be cut.
因此，为了生产马里亚所用的镜子，整条生产线不得不倒过来走。
So to produce the mirrors from Mariah, the entire production line had to be reversed.
原始玻璃先被送去精确裁切至最终尺寸，
The raw glass was first sent to be precisely cut to its final size
然后进行热处理，
and was then heat treated
最后再送回最初的工厂进行新的镜面涂层工艺。
before being returned to its initial factory for the new mirror coating.
除了银质喷镀，镜子还被涂覆了一层铜，以抵御强烈的太阳辐射。
Along with a silver spray, the mirrors were coated with copper to provide resistance against intense solar radiation.
最终成果就是你今天所见的效果——反射率超过90%、
The result is what you see today, a surface with over 90% reflection
能够承受地球上最严酷环境的镜面。
that can withstand some of the harshest conditions on Earth.
说到地球上最严酷的环境，这里还有一个大问题。
Talking of the harshest conditions on Earth, here's a big one.
THE LINE将不会进行户外空调（air conditioned）。
The line will not be airond conditioned.
没错。THE LINE首席开发官在今年早些时候的一次演讲中证实，室外将不设空调。
That's right. The lack of outdoor cooling was confirmed in a presentation by the line's chief development officer earlier this year.
要记住，这不是一栋建筑，而是一座城市。
You've got to remember that this isn't a building, it's a city.
所以，在你的家里、办公室里或者任何室内空间，你可以开足空调。
So, inside your home or your office or wherever, you can have as much air con as you want.
但在街道上，你就暴露在沙漠的自然气温之下。
But out on the streets, you're subject to the ambient temperature of the desert.
如果这还不够糟糕，热岛效应（heat island effect）可能会让情况雪上加霜——
And if that's not bad enough, it could be made worse by the heat island effect,
这是一种城市吸收和积聚热量的程度远超农村地区的现象。
a phenomenon where cities absorb and retain heat much more dramatically than rural areas.
比如，在炎热天气里，伦敦市区可能比周边乡村高出多达5摄氏度，就是因为大量吸热的混凝土建筑。
In hot weather, for example, London can be up to 5° warmer than the surrounding countryside because of all its heat absorbing concrete.
而在THE LINE里，会有大量的混凝土、钢铁和玻璃。
And in the line, there's going to be a lot of concrete and steel and glass.
这是相当严重的问题，但目前我们能依赖的，只是一句保证，
Now, that's pretty major, but currently all we have to go on is an assurance
说这一切都已经过充分考量和建模，
that this has all been thought about and modeled
一切都会没问题。
and that it's all going to be okay.
其中一个论点是，THE LINE墙壁的镜面外观
One argument made is that the mirror finish of the lines walls
将反射大量光线，
is going to reflect so much light
使得城市本身吸收的热量并不会太多。
that the city won't actually absorb that much heat.
我们还被告知，玻璃将具有透气性，以允许空气流通。
We're also told the glass is going to be breathable to allow air to pass through.
至于这究竟意味着巨大的墙壁上会设有通风口，还是正在发明一种全新材料，我们目前无从知晓。
Now, whether that means the vast walls will have vents in them or there's a brand new material being invented, we just don't know.
但这并不能让人感到乐观。
But it doesn't exactly fill you with optimism.
看来，THE LINE里的生活将主要在各个模块中展开。
So, it looks like Life in the Line
is going to be largely lived within modules.
每个模块都被设计为包含你所需的全部基本设施，步行即可抵达。
Each one is being designed to contain all the basic amenities that you need,
accessible within a short walk.
本质上，这是哥本哈根、苏黎世等城市推行的15分钟城市（15-minute city）概念的延伸。
Essentially, it's an extension of the 15-minute city concept
that you see in places like Copenhagen or Zurich.
但要实现这一点，
But for that to be possible,
你必须能在不被烈日烤化的情况下四处走动。
you've got to be able to get around without melting.
如果你需要去更远的地方，就得依靠某种交通方式。
And if you need to go any further, you'll need some form of transportation.
但在探讨交通如何运作之前，
But before we can get stuck into how transport will work,
我们先来解释一下为什么这座城市是一条线。
we need to explain why the line is a line.
所以，看来我们建城市的方式一直都是错的。
So apparently we've all been doing our cities wrong.
这是伦敦，约有860万人口，
This is London, home to about 8.6 million people,
略低于THE LINE全面建成后
just shy of the 9 million people
最终能容纳的900万人。
that could ultimately live in the fully realized line.
它吞噬了英格兰东南部相当大的一块土地。
It swallows up a sizable chunk of the southeast of England.
现在再来看看与THE LINE的对比。
Now look what happens if we compare that to the line.
他们想表达的观点是：这代表着城市建设的旧模式。
The point they're making is that this represents the old way of building cities.
它没有经过任何真正的规划，就这样蔓延生长。
It's grown without any real plan.
它无序扩张，效率低下。
It's sprawling and it's inefficient.
如果我们能把这些人都安置在这座时尚、技术先进的建筑里，
Wouldn't it be much neater if we could take all those people
岂不是好得多？
and house them in this slick, technologically advanced structure?
而要做到这一点，有一样东西必须被彻底淘汰——汽车。
And to do that, there's one key thing you need to get rid of.
Cars.
汽车或许是沙特阿拉伯富裕的重要原因，
Now, cars may be a large part of why Saudi Arabia is rich,
但这里着眼的是未来。
but this is looking to the future.
汽车占用大量空间，还会发生碰撞事故。
Cars take up a lot of space. They crash.
它们必须停放。
They've got to be parked.
它们载不了多少人。
They don't carry many people.
THE LINE承诺的是更好的替代方案。
What the line's promising is something much better.
在最底层，你将看到THE LINE的高速铁路（high-speed railway）。
Here at the bottom, you'll find the lines highspeed railway.
它将连接国际机场与西端。
It's going to connect the international airport to the western tip.
据说全程只需20分钟，
Supposedly, it's going to take 20 minutes to make that whole journey,
这将比当今世界上任何一列火车都要快。
which will be faster than any train in existence today.
在此之上，THE LINE的大众公共交通（mass transit）系统——一套市郊风格的轨道系统——
Above all this, the line's general mass transit, a suburban style rail system,
每隔1.5公里设一站。
will be stopping every 1.5 km.
然后，分布在THE LINE五个主层（primary decks）之间的是一张轻轨（light rail）网络，
Then distributed between the lines five primary decks
每隔100米停靠一次。
will be a light rail network stopping every 100 m.
连接各层之间的是一系列自动扶梯和电梯。
Connecting people between the levels will be a series of escalators and lifts.
这理应是THE LINE的一大卖点——
Now this is supposed to be one of the big selling points of the line
它的形态本身就是一种更好、更高效的城市理念。
that its shape is a better, more efficient concept for a city.
但事实真的如此吗？
But is that really the case?
要回答这个问题，来看看这个。
Well, to answer that, take a look at this.
这是苹果园区（Apple Park），史蒂夫·乔布斯最后的伟大创作。
This is Apple Park, Steve Jobs's last great creation.
它与THE LINE有相似之处——
It's similar to the line
同样拥有一个容纳万物的简洁结构。
in that it has this simple structure that houses everything.
但不同的是，它是一个圆形。
But it's different because it's a circle.
这是刻意为之，因为圆形承载着某种理念。
That was deliberate because a circle embodies certain ideas.
首先，在圆形中没有等级之分，
For one, in a circle, there's no hierarchy,
没有高低之别，没有人人觊觎的转角办公室，
no top or bottom, no coveted corner offices,
内部空间被所有人平等共享。
and the space inside is equally shared by all.
它在通行方面同样出色，说来也不是什么双关——
It's also good for getting around, no pun intended.
任何人需要走的最长路径，
The furthest anyone has to travel
不过是从一侧到另一侧的一条直线。
is a straight line from one side to another.
你需要行走的最大距离，就是建筑的直径。
The maximum distance you have to travel is the diameter of the building.
现在来看看THE LINE。
Now take a look at the line.
如果我想去任何地方，
If I want to travel anywhere,
实际上只有两个选择：向左或向右。
I've only really got two options, head left or head right.
而在一座放射状城市（radial city）中，我可以朝任意方向出发。
Whereas in a radial city, I've got every direction to turn in.
因此，平均行程始终会更短。
So the average journey will always be shorter.
现在，我们再来审视一下那些交通方案。
Now, let's take a look again at those transport options.
我们被告知，
We're being told that we're going to be able to get from here
将能从这里一路抵达THE LINE的另一端——170公里之外——
all the way down to the other end of the line, 170 km away,
仅需20分钟。
in just 20 minutes.
这是中国铁路CR450 AAF型列车。
This is the China Railway CR450 AAF.
它是世界上最快的列车，尽管目前仍在研发阶段。
It's the fastest train in the world, although it's still currently in development.
它的最高时速将达到450公里，
It'll have a top speed of 450 km an hour,
这意味着就连它也无法在20分钟内跑完THE LINE全程。
meaning that not even this could travel the line in 20 minutes.
而且这还没算上加速和减速所需的时间。
And that's without allowing any time for speeding up or slowing down.
此外，它只设两个站，
Plus, it'll only have two stations,
这意味着对于居住在城市中段的人来说，几乎没什么用。
meaning it's not much use for people that live in the middle of the city.
这就意味着，对于其他服务，
It means that for those other services,
你只能依赖每隔1.5公里——大约每英里停靠一次的市郊列车。
you're stuck using a suburban train that stops every 1.5 km
这效率能高到哪去？
or roughly every mile. How efficient is that?
那么，我们走到哪一步了？
So, where are we?
这期视频一开始，我们就说THE LINE和更宏观的NEOM项目
We started this video by saying the line and the wider project NEOM
是2030愿景（Vision 2030）的组成部分——
were part of vision 2030,
一个旨在彻底重塑沙特经济
a plan to kind of totally rewire the Saudi economy
并在这个十年结束前将国家从经济困境中拯救出来的计划。
by the end of the decade and save the country from economic ruin.
时钟正在滴答作响，
Well, that clock is ticking and we don't even know
而我们甚至不知道一期工程（Phase 1）能否在那之前完工。
if phase 1 is going to be complete by then.
就在几个月前，《金融时报》（Financial Times）的一项深度调查披露，
Just a few months ago, a detailed investigation by the Financial Times
高层管理人员私下承认这个项目根本无法实现。
claimed that top level executives were privately admitting that this project was impossible.
这才是整个计划的核心症结所在。
And that's really the crux of the whole scheme.
2021年宣布之时，THE LINE的雄心壮志令人叹为观止。
When it was announced in 2021, the line was so bold in its ambition.
它登上了全球各地的头条新闻。
It made headlines around the world.
它迫使所有人重新审视我们的城市应该是什么样子。
It forced everyone to debate what our city should look like.
它激励了孩子们，让他们对人类未来的故事充满了兴奋与热情。
It inspired kids and got them excited
and engaged about the story of our future.
它是如此天马行空，近乎一种挑衅。
It was so out there that it was almost confrontational.
它在挑战所有人，看谁敢把它一笔勾销。
It dared people to write it off.
此后，每一个展现工程进展的无人机镜头、每一张卫星图像，
And then with every drone shot showing progress, with every satellite image,
都像是对那些质疑者的一次胜利宣言。
they were presented like victory laps over those who had little faith.
但如今已经过去5年了，
But we're 5 years in now
这个项目真的需要开始展现出一些实质性进展了。
and this thing really needs to start showing some progress.
2026年被誉为关键之年。
2026 is being touted as a big year.
这将是一切真正开始成形的一年。
Is the year where things are really going to start to take shape.
但如果这一切没有发生，那就一切都说不准了。
But if that doesn't happen, then all bets are off.
人们很容易这样想：
It's tempting to think that, well, if anyone could build something like this,
如果说有谁能建成这样的东西，那一定是拥有无上权力和雄厚资源的沙特阿拉伯——
it's going to be Saudi Arabia with its unchecked power and its vast resources,
但正如我们所见，这已经不是他们一家能说了算的事了。
but as we've seen, it's not just up to them anymore.
>> 归根结底，一切都取决于钱，
>> Ultimately, it all boils down to money
而这里的钱袋子
and and the purse here is controlled
掌握在这个星球上最富有的人之一手中。
by one of the richest men on the planet.
然而，就目前而言，要完全实现MBS的愿景，
However, at this point, to fully realize what MBS wants,
所需资金将超出那个钱袋子的承载能力，对吧？
it's going to take more money than that purse has, right?
所以这将需要大量来自私人市场的资金注入——
So it's going to take a lot of buyin from the private markets,
外部资本合作伙伴、海外投资者等等。
external capital partners, foreign investors, etc.
但总体而言，
But generally, generally speaking, they want to see a little bit more
他们都希望看到更切实际的假设。
in terms of realistic assumptions.
>> 即便真的建成了，宜居性（livability）仍然是一个问题。
>> Even if it does get built, there's still the question of livability.
这会是一座真正运转的城市吗？
Will this be a functioning city?
它会是一个人们想要居住的地方，还是仅仅供人参观？
Will it be a place people want to live or will they just visit?
>> 你认为十年后这里会是什么样子？
>> What would you see in 10 years time?
有极小的可能性，大概10%吧——
So there's a very tiny chance, 10% maybe,
届时会有一些设施和THE LINE的某一段建成，
that there'll be some facilities and a hunk of the line
富人们会蜂拥而至，来这里叹为观止，
and rich people will go there to marvel at it
而关于进一步建设、更多度假区的承诺仍会不断涌现，
and there will still be promises being made about further construction
或许还会有更多的避难所被建起来。
and further resorts and more and more refues might be built.
我认为更有可能的结果是：大部分都会被废弃。
I think more likely most of it will be abandoned.
>> 毫无疑问，如果这个东西真的建成，
>> There's no question that if this thing gets built
它将是人类历史上有史以来最伟大的建筑之一。
that it'll be one of the greatest things ever built in human history.
堪称当代金字塔。但这是个非常大的"如果"。
the modern-day equivalent of the pyramids. But that's a very big if.
这个项目的根源在于赛博朋克（cyberpunk），
This project has its roots in cyberpunk
而接下来这一年将是决定性的——
and the next year is going to be decisive
它究竟只是停留在科幻小说的想象中，还是会成为科学现实。
in determining whether it stays as just science fiction or becomes science fact.
本视频由AMD赞助播出。
This video was sponsored by AMD.
别忘了，点击下方链接，
Don't forget you can do yourself a favor
了解完整的Threadripper Pro产品线，绝对值得一看。
by clicking that link below and checking out the full Threader Pro lineup.
一如既往，如果你喜欢这期视频，
And as always guys, if you enjoyed this video
想从这个权威的建筑频道获取更多内容，
and you want to get more from the definitive video channel for construction,
记得订阅B1N。
make sure you subscribe to the B1N.